Hey, everyone, and welcome. Have you ever wished you could travel through time?
みなさん、こんにちは。時間旅行ができたらいいなと思ったことはありますか？
Well, guess what? Today, you're getting the keys to your very own time machine.
今日は、あなた自身のタイムマシンの鍵を手に入れます。
We're going to jump into the past and figure out how to talk about all the cool stuff that
過去に飛び込んで、昨日や先週、さらには数年前の出来事を話す方法を学びます。
happened yesterday, or last week, or even years ago. You ready? Let's power this thing up.
準備はいいですか？さあ、始めましょう。
So, you know, talking about right now is pretty easy, right? You can just say,
今のことを話すのは簡単ですよね？例えば、
I am busy today. Simple. But what if the best part of your week happened yesterday?
「今日は忙しい」と言えばいいだけです。シンプルです。でも、もし週の最高の瞬間が昨日だったら？
How do you tell your friends about that awesome concert last night or why you couldn't hang out?
昨夜の素晴らしいコンサートや、なぜ遊べなかったのかを友達にどう伝えますか？
That's the secret code we're going to crack today.
それが今日解決する秘密のコードです。
And yeah, to travel to the past, you need a time machine.
そう、過去に行くにはタイムマシンが必要です。
But forget all that complicated sci-fi stuff.
でも、複雑なSFの話は忘れてください。
I'm giving you the keys to your English time machine.
あなたの英語のタイムマシンの鍵をお渡しします。
And the best part? It's powered by just two super simple words.
しかも、そのために必要なのはたった2つの簡単な言葉です。
Seriously, that's it! Okay, first things first.
本当にそれだけです！では、まずは基本を見てみましょう。
Let's check out the main controls on this time machine of ours.
私たちのタイムマシンの主な操作は、wasとwereです。
Meet, was, and were.
これが私たちを過去に飛ばす魔法のボタンです。
So think about it. For talking about today, the present,
考えてみてください。今日、現在について話すときは、
you've got three words you use all the time, right? Am, is, and are. Like, I am a student.
いつも使う3つの言葉、am、is、areがありますよね？例えば、「私は学生です」。
He is cool. They are at school. Pretty straightforward?
「彼はかっこいい」「彼らは学校にいます」。簡単ですよね？
But get this. Here's the awesome part. When you want to talk about the past,
でも、ここが素晴らしいところです。過去について話すときは、
you only need two words. That's it. So your time machine actually makes English
必要なのはたった2つの言葉だけです。それだけで、タイムマシンは英語を
easier. How cool is that? Forget about three words. All you need are was and were.
簡単にしてくれます。すごいですよね？3つの言葉は忘れて、wasとwereだけで大丈夫です。
So let's break down how this magic works. Take a look. You see how m and is both kind of merge
では、この魔法がどう機能するかを見てみましょう。amとisが合体して
together. They become just one word, was, and are just transforms into were. Just two little
wasになり、areはwereに変わります。たった2つの小さな
changes and boom, you're officially talking about the past. Okay, so here's the number one rule
変更で、過去について話せるようになります。さて、タイムマシンのルールは
for your time machine. It's super simple. You use was when you're talking about just one person or
とてもシンプルです。1人や1つの物について話すときはwasを使います。
thing. You know, I was tired or the pizza was delicious. And you use were when you're talking
例えば、「私は疲れていた」や「ピザは美味しかった」。そして、2人以上の人や
to you or about more than one person. You were right or my friends were late. See, one versus
あなたに話すときはwereを使います。「あなたは正しかった」や「友達は遅れた」。1つと
more than one. Alright, every good machine needs special features. And our time machine is no
2つ以上の違いです。さて、良い機械には特別な機能が必要です。私たちのタイムマシンも
different. What about talking about stuff that didn't happen? Well, for that, we have the
同様です。起こらなかったことについて話すには、Notボタンがあります。見てみましょう。
Not button. Let's check it out.
これがどれほど簡単か信じられないでしょう。
And you're not going to believe how easy this is.
ステップ1、タイムマシンの言葉、wasかwereを見つけます。
Step one, find your time machine word, was or were.
ステップ2、その後にnotを付けるだけです。それだけです。
Step two, just stick the word not right after it. That's literally it.
本当に他に変更はありません。とても簡単です。
Seriously, no other changes. So simple.
では、実際に見てみましょう。
Let's see this thing in action.
例えば、「彼は忙しかった」という文があります。
So you have a sentence like, he was busy.
でも、あなたが伝えたい話ではないかもしれません。
But maybe that's not the story you want to tell.
そこで、notを入れると「彼は忙しくなかった」になります。
So you just pop in not and suddenly he was not busy.
「彼らは疲れていた」も同様で、「彼らは疲れていなかった」になります。
Same thing for they were tired.
過去の出来事のストーリーを変えているだけです。
Okay, pro tip time. If you want to sound supernatural, like you hear people talk in American movies or
さて、プロのヒントです。アメリカの映画やYouTubeで聞くような自然な話し方をしたいなら、
on YouTube, listen up. We almost always shorten these. So, was not becomes wasn't, and were not
耳を傾けてください。私たちはこれをほぼ常に短縮します。was notはwasn'tになり、were notは
becomes weren't. Go ahead and try saying them. They just roll off the tongue a little easier,
weren'tになります。試してみてください。言いやすくなりますよね。
right? Way more casual. Alright, quick challenge for you. How would you say this in English?
もっとカジュアルです。さて、あなたへのクイックチャレンジです。これを英語でどう言いますか？
Got it? The answer is, I was not hungry yesterday. Or if you're using that pro
分かりましたか？答えは「I was not hungry yesterday」です。プロのヒントを使うなら、
tip, I wasn't hungry yesterday. Nice. You totally got this. Okay, buckle up for
「I wasn't hungry yesterday」です。素晴らしい！あなたはこれを完全に理解しています。さて、次のセクションに進みましょう。
section three. This is my favorite part. This is where you get to be a time
これは私のお気に入りの部分です。あなたはタイム探偵になります。
detective. You're gonna use your new skills to ask questions and find out
新しいスキルを使って、他の人が過去に何をしていたのかを尋ねます。
what everyone else was up to in the past. So how do you ask a question about
過去について質問するには、ただ1つのシンプルな動きです。秘密のトリックのようです。
about the past, it's just one simple move. It's like a secret trick.
wasかwereを見つけて、それを文の先頭に移動させるだけです。
All you do is find was or were and you just slide it all the way
そして、疑問符を付けるだけ。それが全ての秘密です。見てください。
to the front of the sentence. Then just tack on a question mark.
「彼女は疲れていた」という文が「彼女は疲れていた？」に変わります。
That's the whole secret. Check this out. See how the words just flip?
wasを前に移動させただけです。同じことがwereにも当てはまります。
A statement like, she was tired
「あなたは家にいた」は「あなたは家にいた？」になります。
flips into the question, was she tired?
これだけ簡単です。そして、これらの質問に答えるのもとても簡単です。
You were at home becomes the question, were you at home?
「はい」か「いいえ」で始めるだけです。
then say who, and then use your time machine word.
誰かを言ったら、タイムマシンの言葉を使って。
So if someone asks, were you busy? You can say, yes, I was.
誰かに「忙しかった？」と聞かれたら、はい、忙しかったと答えられます。
Or was she tired? No, she wasn't. It's a really simple pattern.
「彼女は疲れていた？」と聞かれたら、いいえ、疲れていなかったと答えます。とても簡単なパターンです。
Okay, Detective, one last practice round.
では、探偵さん、最後の練習問題です。
How would you ask this question in English?
この質問を英語でどう聞きますか？
Think about that secret move. You got it?
その秘密の動きを考えてみて。分かりましたか？
The answer is, were they busy last night?
答えは「彼らは昨夜忙しかったですか？」です。
See, we just took were and slid it right to the front.
ほら、wereを前に持ってきただけです。
You're a total pro at this now.
今やあなたは完全にプロです。
And just like that, we're at our final section.
そして、こうして私たちは最終セクションに来ました。
You've learned the controls, you've practiced your moves,
コントロールを学び、動きを練習しました。
and now congratulations. I'm happy to announce that you are officially
おめでとうございます。あなたは正式に
an English time traveler. So let's do a quick recap.
英語のタイムトラベラーです。では、簡単に振り返りましょう。
Here's your time machine's control panel, all in one place.
こちらがタイムマシンのコントロールパネルです。
Use was for one person, use were for you, and for more than one.
一人にはwas、あなたにはwere、複数にはwereを使います。
To say no, just add not right after was or were.
「いいえ」と言うには、wasまたはwereの後にnotを加えます。
And to ask a question, just move was or were to the very front.
質問をするには、wasまたはwereを前に持ってきます。
That's the whole guide right there, all you need to know.
これが全てのガイドです。知っておくべきことはこれだけです。
So your journey is really just getting started.
あなたの旅はこれから始まります。
You now have this awesome power to tell any story from your past.
過去のどんな物語でも語る力を手に入れました。
So I have a question for you.
では、質問があります。
Now that you're officially a time traveler,
正式にタイムトラベラーになった今、
what's the first story you're going to tell? Think about it.
最初に語る物語は何ですか？考えてみてください。
Thanks so much for hanging out with me today.
今日は一緒にいてくれてありがとう。